<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902"
   docName="draft-chuang-ietf-bimi-security-perspectives-00">
<front>
<title abbrev="VMC Security Perspective">
Verified Mark Certificates Proposal: A Security Perspective
</title>
<author initials="W." surname="Chuang" fullname="Weihaw Chuang" role="editor">
    <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
	<address>
	  <email>weihaw@google.com</email>
	</address>
</author>
<author initials="T." surname="Loder" fullname="Thede Loder" role="editor">
	<organization>Skye Logicworks</organization>
	<address>
    <email>thede@skyelogicworks.com</email>
	</address>
</author>
<date month="March" year="2019" />
<area>General</area>
<workgroup>Application Area Working Group</workgroup>
<keyword>LOGOTYPE</keyword>
<keyword>email</keyword>

<abstract>

<t>
This document motivates the need for embedding logotypes in X.509
certificates along with the certificate validation process from a
security perspective.
</t>

</abstract>
</front>
<middle>

<section anchor="objectives" title="Objectives">
<t>
Many Mail User Agents and mail systems provide logo imagery as avatars
as part of the user interface chrome.  For branded email, the agents
and systems use different, proprietary methods for provisioning the
avatar which causes consistency problems.  Instead there should a
common, internet scale, secure method to fetch the sender’s brand logo
indicators during message delivery which this document along with
others documents by the AuthIndicators Working Group (aka BIMI Working
Group) propose.
</t>
<t>
Given the potential for impersonation abuse if not safeguarded, the
proposal incorporates defense in depth as it assumes an adversarial
security model and that parties will attempt to exploit
sender/subscribers for their own criminal benefit.  Due to this risk
of identity spoofing, a sender’s identity is verified by a Certificate
Authority (CA) that acts as a Mark Verification Authority (MVA) that
then issues X.509 certificate with this evidence as a Verified Mark
Certificate (VMC).  One risk is that the MVA may fail to distinguish a
spoofed identity during their verification either by oversight or
intentionally.  To enable detection, issued certificates are publicly
disclosed through permanent untamperable logs that can be verified by
receivers, trademark monitors, the trademark holders themselves, and
other interested parties.  Because of this, email receivers will have
greater confidence that the sender’s logo is what the sender says they
are.
</t><t>
The logo may be presented to the recipient if the email is at a
minimum authenticated via SPF <xref target="RFC7208"/>, or DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"/>,
and passes the DMARC <xref target="RFC7489"/> policy check.  Because this proposal
uses domain authentication and DMARC in order for the logo to be
shown, it incentivizes the use of these domain authentication and
authorization methods.  These methods are important because they
provide a consistent means of protecting against an sender domain
spoofing.  However the FTC Office of Technology Research and
Investigation in 2017 found that 66% of business mail domains did not
use DMARC.  Logo carrying mail must also pass other receiver
requirements such as not phish and not spam per their own policies.
Domain-based authentication methods SPF, and DKIM, enables the email
receivers’ automated anti-abuse systems to tie together emails sent by
the same sender to generate accurate per domain reputations that allow
them to filter abusive emails.  The Verified Mark Certificate contains
curated sender’s metadata, that provides additional signals for
anti-phishing.
</t>
<t>
This document builds on the more generalized brand logo association
drafts that is specified in <xref target="I-D.blank-ietf-bimi"/> and
<xref target="I-D.brotman-ietf-bimi-guidance"/>.  This document is meant to
motivate the purpose for Verified Mark Certificates, and is purely
informative.  The <xref target="roadmap">Roadmap</xref> section calls out where normative documents
are needed. 
</t>

<section anchor="objectives-critique" title="Critique of the BIMI Proposals">
  <section anchor="objectives-bimi-draft" title="BIMI Draft">
  <t>
    The <xref target="I-D.blank-ietf-bimi"/>, dated February 6, 2019
    aka the “Assertion Record” specification, states as its objectives
    the following goals:
    <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>No dependency on new Internet protocols or services for indicator registration or revocation</t>
      <t>Incremental deployment</t>
      <t>Policies solely published in BIMI DNS (TXT) record</t>
      <t>Delegation by logo owners to third party logo providers</t>
      <t>Scalability of brand associations across internet scale of domains</t>
      <t>Uniformity of brands displayed</t>
    </list>
(BIMI stands for Brand Indicators for Message Identification) The
Assertion Record draft uses SPF/DKIM/DMARC for message verification.
It defines optional header metadata and defaults to determine from
where to fetch the logo policy and locator from BIMI DNS TXT records.
From these, the receiver can generate a URL to fetch the logo.  It
succeeds with the above goals, however it admits an important
limitation in that it does not specify "verification and reputation"
mechanisms and depends on them to prevent abuse.  This document
describes solutions for those limitations.
  </t>
  <section anchor="objectives-thread-modeling" title="BIMI Draft Threat Modeling">
    <t>
      Because some of the uses of branded email are high-value
      transactional and business emails, there is the possibility the
      protocol might be abused.  Consequently the following is a
      threat model to identify security weaknesses in the above
      protocol.  Malicious senders may spoof trusted identities for
      phishing or spam by copying brand identities or by creating a
      similar but confusable logo, served from their domain with their
      own domain authentication.  A adversary could:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t>game the receiver’s reputation system by using <eref target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/46d6/7fceac97a55fe9981b2d420f3b0c357be00c.pdf">automated networks</eref> to send good email traffic and then launch an attack.</t>
	<t>related concern, is the problem of low traffic senders that receivers will have difficulty determining reputation.</t>
      </list>

      An explicit definition of trustworthiness may be helpful establishing a reputation in these circumstances.
    </t><t>      
      Another attack is to exploit the vulnerability of the email
      system by injecting emails crafted by the adversary that use the
      good sender's identity.  While BIMI uses message authentication
      through SPF/DKIM/DMARC that is meant to prevent this type of
      spoofing, the adversary could exploit domains with weak
      authentication via:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t><eref target="https://research.google.com/pubs/archive/43962.pdf">overly broad SPF</eref> policies acceptance policies</t>
	<t><eref target="https://www.wired.com/2012/10/dkim-vulnerability-widespread/">weak DKIM keys</eref></t>
      </list>

      Fortunately good senders can easily fix this.  The adversary
      could exploit weaknesses in DNS integrity as message
      authentication depends on the integrity of the SPF/DKIM/DMARC
      records which may be attacked through DNS cache poisoning or
      man-in-the-middle (MitM).  While such attacks seem far fetched,
      the <eref
      target="https://www.wired.com/2014/03/quantum/">Snowden
      disclosures</eref> show that nation-state adversaries have been
      able to mount such attacks.  Unfortunately deployment of DNS
      protection through DNSSEC <eref
      target="https://blog.apnic.net/2017/12/06/dnssec-deployment-remains-low/">seems
      to be stalled</eref>.
    </t>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="objectives-bimi-guidance" title="BIMI Guidance (So far) About Certificates">
    <t>
      The <xref target="I-D.brotman-ietf-bimi-guidance"/> dated on 6 Feb 6 2019
      aka “Receivers Guidance” extends and provides best practices for
      the Assertion Records draft. It notes the use of Verified Mark
      Certificates which is new certificate issued by Mark Verifying
      Authorities (MVA) to resist the spoofing attacks though with
      limited details on validation and usage.  The Receivers Guidance
      document states receivers should work with multiple MVAs to
      allow the successful untrust of any one malicious MVA.  It also
      calls for receivers to partner with Dispute Resolution Agencies
      to handle trademark conflicts as well as acknowledges the courts
      primacy for conflict resolution.  It has other guidance: it
      notes that receivers MTA may fetch and store the logo for the
      MUA or it may have the MUA fetch it itself.  It also provides
      deployment guidance on domain authentication and DMARC.
    </t>
    <t>
      The Receiver Guidance document references an AuthIndicators
      Working Group document <eref
      target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OzL9FqexZpZJQuoqAK2E3sXjOwEcLNCvXW7e88Olt2I/edit?usp=sharing">“Verified
      Mark Certificates Usage (for review)”</eref> dated 23 October
      2018 for details about Verified Mark Certificates.  That
      document is a specification on the handling of Verified Mark
      Certificates by the receiver MTA and recipient MUA.  It defines
      the VMC validation and fetch process designed to protect the
      privacy for the recipient from the sender- VMC fetch occurs at
      delivery time, and cached by the MTA for use by the MUA, thus
      view time usage of the VMC is hidden from the sender.  Similarly
      Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs) are specified to allow for
      offline revocation checking of the certificate.  (There is the
      related scenario of keeping private the use of the VM
      Certificate content by the recipient from the receiver.  This
      hasn’t been specified in any of the documents, but a likely
      solution would be embed the logo as a new header for use by the
      MUA)
    </t><t>
      Notably those two documents avoid detailed discussion on the use
      of Verified Mark Certificates for which this document tries to
      fill in.  Moreover, there are potential operational risks with
      using curated information provided by X.509 certificates that
      this document discusses next.
    </t>
    <section anchor="objectives-problems-certificates" title="Problems with Certificates">
      <t>
	Experience using identity carrying certificates have
	identified several important issues.  An adversary attempting
	to spoof an identity might try to exploit weaknesses in
	certificate issuance validation.
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>Lax or intentionally malicious validation by CA/MVA may allow an adversary to impersonate with a copied or look alike identity.</t>
	  <t>Ambiguities in the registered identity that the CA/MVA checks against may allow an adversary to obtain an “legitimate” identity for spoofing.  Note that arguably the CA/MVA validation is considered successful here.
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t><eref target="https://stripe.ian.sh/">Carroll</eref> demonstrated in 2017 that ambiguities caused by different jurisdictions allowed him to obtain a web EV certificate for "Stripe, Inc." in Kentucky that could have allowed him to spoof the better known "Stripe, Inc" in Delaware.  While browsers displays differences in country jurisdiction, it does not show state level information, and even if it did, it is doubtful users would notice.  The analog for logos is that an adversary that desires spoofing logos in one jurisdiction would register similar or identical logos in another.</t>
	    <t><eref target="https://typewritten.net/write/ev-phishing/">Burton</eref> similarly demonstrated that he could obtain a web EV certificate for a misleading company name with a positive sounding security message e.g. "Identity Verified".  The analog logo attack might be that the adversary registers a checkmark or padlock logo.
</t>
	    <t>"Cousin marks" are similar but legitimate logos add another dimension of confusability as illustrated by <eref target="http://whatculture.com/offbeat/10-massive-companies-unbelievably-similar-logos">this list</eref>.  This confusability of this list seems to be caused by the trademark registration agency allowing similar logos when the company’s line of business don’t overlap. </t>	    
	  </list></t>
	</list>

With these spoofing attacks, one issue has been understanding the
scope of the attack i.e. given one bad certificate, if there are other
ones.  Lack of global visibility in what has been issued has
historically made this problematic.
    </t><t>
The largest deployed set of these identity carrying certificates has
been web Extended Validation (EV) where the subscribers legal identity
gets additional validation.  Web sites uses these EV certificates get
additional chrome e.g. historically a green “bar” containing the
company name and padlock indicator.  However operational experience
has indicated problems with this approach:

<list style="symbols">
<t><eref target="http://www.usablesecurity.org/papers/jackson.pdf">Jackson et al.</eref> found that using the web EV green padlock UI as a positive security indicator was not effective in helping users distinguish good websites from phishing as users did not notice the indicators. </t>
<t>Company names sometime are not familiar to users.  For example Google’s parent company name is “Alphabet Inc” which likely isn’t as familiar as “Google”.</t>
</list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
</section><!--Objectives-->


<section anchor="vmc" title="Verified Mark Certificate">
  <t>
    This section specifies issuing a BIMI-specific X.509 certificate
    that binds logos and other information to domains and to a legal
    entity.  CA/MVAs validate the binding and the X.509 CA based PKI
    proves to all parties that this validation was done.  These
    certificates are called Verified Mark Certificates (VMC or VM
    Certificates aka Mark Verified Certificates or MVC in some of our
    other documents).  This document primarily works with the use of
    registered trademarks as it provides a useful legal framework to
    establish VMC upon, however the AuthIndicators working group is
    evaluating how to expand that to include other non-registered
    identities.
  </t>
  <section anchor="vmc-association-logo" title="Certificate Association With Logo">
    <t>
Existing work provides specification for brand logos in X.509 PKIX
certificates as specified in <xref target="RFC3709"/> and <xref
target="RFC6170"/>.  The logo images can be embedded within the X.509
certificate as a subject extension <xref target="RFC3709"/> using a DATA URL mentioned
in <xref target="RFC6170"/> and specified in <xref target="RFC2397"/>.  The certificate
subject identifier describes a legal owner of the brand that can be
used for verification, and a DNS domain that matches the sender's
email address domain.  The validation of these identities can follow
the procedures in <eref
target="https://cabforum.org/wp-content/uploads/EV-V1_6_6.pdf">CABF EV
baseline 1.6</eref> with additional guidelines specific for BIMI as
described in these <eref
target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/10IzxkdrveDazBAvTvOUa9uCIDBwMkdmluwHEcbja42w/edit?usp=sharing">Guidelines
for Issuance of Verified Mark Certificates v0.97</eref>.
    </t><t>
The Verified Mark Certificate must chain-up to a well known public
trust anchor i.e. a well known Certificate Authority certificate
issuer.  This provides a cryptographic means to prove that a domain
owns a brand to the relying party as long as they can trust the
transitive issuing policy.  If the logo bearing certificate is a CA
certificate, then it must be name constrained to the owning domain or
subdomain.  This prevents the brand from being wrongly associated with
some non-owning domain for some child entity certificate issued from
the CA certificate.

<xref target="RFC3709"/> allows the specification of only one logo per certificate.  The issuer may need to issue multiple certificates that bear different logos for the brand.  The appropriate logo is optionally selected by the BIMI email header as mentioned in <xref target="I-D.blank-ietf-bimi"/> or defaults to the default for the organizational domain name.  

    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-verified-identity" title="Verified Identity of Sender">
    <t>
 The Verified Mark Certificate issuance process builds upon the web
 <eref
 target="https://cabforum.org/wp-content/uploads/EV-V1_6_1.pdf">Extended
 Validation (EV)</eref> certificates issuance guidelines, with
 appropriate extensions as described <eref
 target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/10IzxkdrveDazBAvTvOUa9uCIDBwMkdmluwHEcbja42w/edit?usp=sharing">Guidelines
 for Issuance of Verified Mark Certificates v0.97</eref>.  In
 particular the brand ownership must undergo rigorous validation by
 the issuing CA back to that legal entity, including explicit
 face-to-face identity validation of the applicant.  CAs already have
 experience validating internet domain ownership back to legal
 entities for the web EV program, and it would be reasonably feasible
 for them to examine brand IP as well since these may be registered in
 government trademark registries i.e. the logos must match a
 registered trademark as described later.  In addition brand names may
 also be specified and found in those registries, as often they are
 more easily recognized than the owning company’s name.  CAs
 performing these additional vetting steps would act as the Mark
 Verifying Authorities (MVA) mentioned earlier.  Further, the
 requesting party for the certificates must meet certain minimum
 identification and formation requirement e.g. be an incorporated
 company, government body or registered non-profit known in the public
 record.  The requesting party’s legal address is disclosed in the
 certificate for identification by the recipient and other interested
 parties following the practices of the trademark jurisdiction.  For
 example here's the <eref
 target="https://www.uspto.gov/trademarks-application-process/faqs-personal-information-trademark-records">link
 to USPTO</eref> FAQ, and the <eref
 target="https://euipo.europa.eu/tunnel-web/secure/webdav/guest/document_library/contentPdfs/data_protection/EUIPOs_explanatory_note_en.pdf">link
 for EU</eref> (on page 3).  This also in some hopefully limited
 circumstance may help an aggrieved party serve legal notice.
    </t><t>
 In summary the VMC Guidelines validation process proves that:
 <list style="symbols">
   <t>Legal entity is legitimate</t>
   <t>Domain names are controlled by the organization</t>
   <t>Person requesting the certificate
   <list style="symbols">
     <t>Duly and currently authorized to do so by the organization</t>
     <t>Who they say they are</t>
   </list>
   </t>
   <t>Legal entity has the rights to display the trademark logo (design mark) and optionally name (text mark)</t>
 </list>
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-root-program" title="Root Program">
    <t>
BIMI-aware email receivers and/or mail clients should maintain their
own trusted BIMI CA/MVA root certificate store programs, or otherwise
rely on a program by another receiver.  Such programs would manage a
fixed set of BIMI root certificates managed much like browser root
certificates.  Most importantly these BIMI root certificate set owners
must create a security program to monitor the performance of CA/MVA to
adhere to their CPS much like the browser programs.  A fixed root
certificate set creates certainty for the sender and recipients and
mitigates some BIMI header attacks.  Certain receivers could publish
their root CAs, which would make it possible for intended certificate
subscribers to identify supported CAs. It also moves much of the
security work to the email receivers from the sender, which are better
positioned to do this work due to their security staffing and
association with browser security teams (with their expertise in X.509
PKI security).
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-certificate-transparency" title="Certificate Transparency">
    <t>
      We also propose that these certificates be published in
      Certificate Transparency logs <xref target="RFC6962"/> analogous to those
      operated for web EV certificates.  Certificate Transparency (CT)
      logs are append only which provides protection against
      equivocation i.e. manipulating the logs to show different views
      to different requesters.  A VM Certificate proves that it is
      published in a CT log by including a SCT extension generated
      when logged.  All relying parties must check for the presence of
      the valid SCT, and reject the certificate if it is not present.
      Mandatory publishing provides global transparency that makes it
      easier to detect other similar impersonation attacks or
      mis-issuance.  Global transparency provides certainty once a
      problem has been detected that it can be fully remedied and
      contained.
      </t><t>
      While RFC3709 may allow an external logo with a secure hash
      which may be convenient, an adversary may simply not supply
      potentially incriminating logo during an investigation.  Instead
      we propose embedding the logos in the Verified Mark Certificate.
      With this the VMC CT log also provides a catalog of curated
      logos and their ownership in a machine readable form that may
      then be used by anti-abuse systems for use as reference
      identities.
      </t><t>
      This document proposes that the major mail systems
      using VMC along with VMC issuing CAs should run their own
      publicly visible CT logs.  While logging may be done
      collaboratively, there must always be enough diversity so that
      multiple logs are available under separate ownership to prevent
      conflict of interest.  Mail systems can elect to require logging
      to their CT log in order to show the logos.
      </t><t>
      While some companies (e.g. Google) already actively monitors the
      CT logs for misissuance, many companies don’t that should
      monitor CT logs.  This document encourages the development of
      log monitoring services in particular visual logo monitoring to
      protect brands from spoofing.  For example, it is conceivable
      that a CA may be interested in providing issuing and monitoring
      service for brands as part of their commercial offering.  Along
      those lines there are companies specialized in mark monitoring
      e.g. <eref
      target="https://www.markmonitor.com/">MarkMonitor</eref> that
      might be interested.  Automated visual recognition of logos is a
      capability commercially available e.g. <eref
      target="https://www.brandwatch.com/blog/top-image-recognition-tools">top
      8 list</eref>.
    </t><t>
Beyond that we also propose research into pre-publication of the
certificate in the CT logs before issuance that allows trademark
monitors to detect and block issuance if necessary.  These monitors
would follow the log to look for trademark infringement, improperly
created certificates, and other abuses, and can file complaints to the
log.  If the conflict is not initially resolved between the parties on
he log, then the trademark owners have access to the courts.
Assuming the research into CT with preview, which is being
investigated by the AuthIndicators working group, proves its
feasibility, this can potentially be followed up with standards work.

      
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-registered-trademark" title="Registered Trademark">
    <t>
Using registered trademark helps clarifies ownership of the logo, and
raises the difficulty of succeeding at impersonation. The registration
process in many jurisdictions requires that the trademark be
distinctive and non-confusable with another.  To enforce this, many
jurisdictions use a public review period and brands already employ
brand <eref
target="https://secureyourtrademark.com/blog/trademark-101-monitoring-strategies-can-implement/">monitors</eref>
to protect the trademarks.  As part of this review, many jurisdictions
have tests for objectionable or deceptive marks e.g. “Identity
Verified”.  It also provides a central authority that documents
existing trademarks where an issuing CA/MVA can match the submitted
embedded logo to the documented trademark.  If there is a dispute
between non-fraudulent parties, registration provides access to the
courts, and consequently trademark conflict resolution becomes a
process of following the court process.  The certificate identifies
the trademark owner in case it is necessary to start those legal
proceedings.  </t>

    <t> One issue is jurisdiction as trademarks laws and practices
    differ.  This proposes that the smallest scope should be nation
    level where trademark law is well established.  Trademarks may
    also be registered internationally (across 90+ countries) via the
    Madrid union and due to the universal first world coverage of the
    Madrid union and largely the rest of the world, such a trademark
    can be considered global jurisdiction.  Similarly well known
    regional, multi-country jurisdictions e.g EU should be
    distinguishable as well. The country code information can be
    specified in the certificate trademark jurisdiction field.
    Display of the brand logo/name information should follow where the
    information is valid, and this can be done by displaying the logo
    only when the client is within the jurisdiction to the best of the
    client's ability e.g. GPS on mobile devices, and IP geolocation on
    desktop computers.  A second closely related issue is the strength
    of a particular jurisdiction trademark review and legal system to
    prevent fraudulent trademarks.  A concern is that they may differ
    in their ability to prevent spoofing.  The AuthIndicators Working
    Group in conjunction with the CA/MVA and mail systems will review
    and publish findings on the strength of particular jurisdictions.
    International cross border registration or multiple jurisdiction
    registration maybe helpful when some countries have better
    trademark databases than others and should be encouraged.
      
    </t>
    <section anchor="vmc-coexistance-non" title="Coexistence with non-Registered Trademark">
      <t>
This document extends the supported types in <xref
target="I-D.blank-ietf-bimi"/> to include Verified Mark Certificates
but does not preclude the other logo image types mentioned in there.
In fact this proposal explicitly calls for supporting other logos
policies as the requirements in this document may be too onerous.
There are many reasonable use cases as documented in <eref
target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/10IzxkdrveDazBAvTvOUa9uCIDBwMkdmluwHEcbja42w/edit#bookmark=id.r701mosrrfx3">VMC
Guidelines document section 5</eref> that don’t have registered
trademarks, or need VMC validation. Those other scenarios may use base
images types as allowed in <xref target="I-D.blank-ietf-bimi"/> or may
be X.509 certificates perhaps following their own validation profile
but won’t be described as Verified Mark Certificates.  Furthermore
there may be non-branded scenarios but validateable scenarios such as
profile picture of an individual that could be embedded in VM
Certificates.  Ultimately we want allow senders and receivers
flexibility in choosing which security, authentication and
authorization profile they wish to support and use.
    </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-logo-format" title="Logo Image Format">
    <t>
 The format of the logo is governed by <xref target="RFC3709"/> and
 <xref target="RFC6170"/>.  This document proposes that the logo media
 be encapsulated and represented as <eref
 target="https://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/">SVG vector graphics</eref> so
 that the image representation supports arbitrary visual rescaling.
 This has several advantages.  First, the logo image will always
 appear sharp no matter the display resolution.  Brand owners would
 likely prefer the brand logo to appear in the client without image
 display artifacts like pixelation.  Second, having the ability to
 render the logo in arbitrary many sizes assists in creating logo
 detection neural networks as it eases training those neural networks.
 The general idea is for automatic creation of the training dataset is
 creations of different appearances of the logo with different sizes
 and locations.  Such logo detection neural networks assists in
 automated detection and trademark abuse prevention both in the avatar
 and the message body.  A third advantage of standardizing on one
 scalable image format is that it makes logo similarity comparison
 more deterministic.
    </t>
<t>
  One issue is the security of SVG.  <xref target="RFC6170"/> specifies restrictions on the SVG to secure it:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>Use SVG Tiny profile</t>
    <t>No script</t>
    <t>No external resource references</t>
  </list>
Only images that meet these requirements from RFC6170 are acceptable for use with BIMI and must be validated by the CA/MVA.
    </t>
  </section>
 <section anchor="vmc-non-display" title="Non-Display of Logo">
   <t>
Certificates that claim to Verified Mark Certificates that do not
follow these specifications must be ignored by the receivers and mail
clients, meaning that mail associated with these certificates would
have no brand symbol attached in the UI.  Aside from the obvious
safety benefits, this provides an incentive for certificate issuers
and brand-owning domain registrants to follow these requirements.
Also, receivers are not bound to show the logo if they believe the
message is malicious or fraudulent such as when the receiver believes
the message is spammy or phishy.  As noted above, when the mail client
believes that the user is outside the jurisdiction of the trademark,
then the logo should not be shown.  If the Verified Mark Certificate
has expired, the mail client should not show the logo, though still
permitted to do so for UI continuity.  If the Verified Mark
Certificate is revoked, the mail client must not show the logo.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="vmc-bimi-fetch" title="BIMI Message Fetch">
    <t>
 This normative description of this section is found in the Verified Mark Certificate Usage document, and the content here is provided to expand upon that description. 
    </t>
  <section anchor="vmc-mail-client" title="Mail Clients Support">
    <t>
A BIMI-aware IMAP client or proprietary client upon receiving a BIMI
verified message fetches the logo and displays the logo alongside the
message both in message view and threaded view.  It should be placed
in a location distinct from the message body, in a way that prevents
message body content from spoofing the logo.  It should be visually
distinct from non-BIMI verified messages as many mail clients provides
the means to display a profile image that might be used to spoof a
BIMI verified logo.  Some ideas are to make the BIMI verified logo
larger, different shape or use animation.  Also the UI should support
display of extra descriptive information in case the recipient is
unfamiliar with the logo.  This could be a tooltip or card panel.
This information should include the curated trademark name name if
available, description of the sender, and the jurisdiction of the logo
from the Verified Mark Certificate subject.  As the ability of users
to <eref
target="https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/45366.pdf">understand
and recognize the logo</eref> across different mail user agents
depends on consistency, AuthIndicators working group should create a
voluntary guideline and encourage standard behavior across the email
clients.  This guideline should updated periodically with input from
all BIMI members developing mail clients, taking into account current
and future mail client UIs.  As noted earlier there are circumstances
where the mail client does not display the logo, and instead reverts
to the non-BIMI display behavior.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security">
  <section anchor="security-discussion" title="Discussion">
    <t>
      The proposal in this document attempts to create defense in
      depth.  If a malicious domain attempts to spoof a brand using
      the techniques in this document, there are several preventative
      safeguards.  In order for the malicious domain to create and use
      a Verified Mark Certificate, they must convince a CA/MVA to
      issue one that they can publish.  For arbitrary claimed
      logos/names the CA/MVA vetting process should be able to detect
      the spoofed trademark i.e. lack of a registered trademark, and
      prevent them from being issued.  A malicious domain could
      register a similar confusable trademark, but some of these will
      be prevented by the trademark registration review process.  For
      those that are registered, these may pass CA/MVA validation.  If
      CT with preview becomes reality and these certificates are
      pre-published in that previewable log as proposed earlier,
      trademark monitors can detect spoofed trademark, block issuance
      and if necessary file a court action against the owner of the
      wrongly claimed trademark.  When the certificate has already
      been issued, the aggrieved owner can go to court.  Upon court
      resolution against the infringing confusable logo/name (or upon
      an injunction issued prior to a final resolution), the CA/MVA
      can revoke the Verified Mark Certificate.  A malicious domain
      may try to forge email with a valid RFC822.FROM domain aligned
      with a valid brand bearing domain and BIMI header that uses that
      brand, but whose body contains spam or phishing.  This should
      fail SPF/DKIM message authentication which prevents the brand
      logo from being shown.  The logos provided in the VMC can be
      used for anti-phishing models to help prevent spoofing of
      legitimate mails.  At the final step this proposal provides
      visual branding imagery to help the recipient identify the
      sender.  </t>


    <t> Visual security indicators have been a controversial topics
    since <eref
    target="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~tygar/papers/Why_Johnny_Cant_Encrypt/OReilly.pdf.">“Why
    Johnny Can’t Encrypt”</eref> which noted that users have a hard
    time understanding security concepts. As noted earlier, <eref
    target="http://www.usablesecurity.org/papers/jackson.pdf">subsequent
    research</eref> indicated that web EV security indicators did not
    seem to have an effect on stopping phishing as users seemingly
    tend to ignore positive security indicators.  More recent by <eref
    target="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/soups2016/soups2016-paper-porter-felt.pdf">Felt
    et al.</eref> provided a more nuanced view in that positive
    security indicators have some effect on user decision making but
    was weaker than negative indicators.  Research is needed to see if
    that brand recognition can have an effect albeit perhaps more
    weakly on security decisions.  Users already have a positive
    association with brands since brand owners are incentivized to
    build brand equity by associating their brand with a quality
    product or service.  Brand owners then go about educating
    consumers, allowing them to have <eref
    target="https://faculty.fuqua.duke.edu/~moorman/Marketing-Strategy-Seminar-2015/Session%203/Keller.pdf">strong
    brand recall and discrimination</eref>.  This research is ongoing
    in the AuthIndicators working group.  Care must be taken though
    because the adversary will try to spoof positive security
    indicators which will <eref
    target="http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~tygar/papers/Phishing/why_phishing_works.pdf">dupe
    the user</eref>.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="security-x509" title="X.509 Message Authentication Proposal">
    <t>
The proposed updates to BIMI in this document improve its security
profile, but there still are some security weaknesses for an adversary
to exploit.  First, if SPF message authentication is used, it is
subject to MitM message modification.  Second, both SPF/DKIM message
authentication are subject to DNS record attacks either through MitM
or DNS cache poisoning.  Third, BIMI depends on three separate
mechanisms- DKIM or SPF/DMARC/BIMI to work right.  A relatively simple
improvement to both reduce failure modes and attack surface is to
mandate the use of DKIM style full body message authentication to
resist message modification and use the private-key associated with
the Verified Mark Certificate to sign the DKIM signature.  Verified
Mark Certificate aware receivers can use the certificate public key to
verify the message signature contained in the DKIM header, and can
skip the DKIM DNS record lookup.  For backwards compatibility this
verification can still leverages DKIM with its headers, and DNS record
with the same public key as Verified Mark Certificate, which allows
non BIMI-aware email receivers to use the DKIM for message
authentication.  While this still uses DNS to locate information and
even allows the use of the DKIM public key, receivers aware of
Verified Mark Certificates do not need to depend on DNS to assert
identity and instead uses cryptographic proof via X.509 issuer-signed
certificate that chains up to a CA root certificate instead.  Care
must be taken with approach to prevent downgrade attacks say between
the approach in this section and that of the rest of this document.
Because of the additional complexity and newness, this idea is
relegated to future discussion.
    </t>
  </section>
</section><!--Security-->

<section anchor="roadmap" title="Roadmap">
    <t>
      This informational document describes the rationale for Verified
      Mark Certificates.  This presumes several normative,
      specification documents: 1) Verified Mark Certificate profile
      and policy, 2) Verified Mark Certificate handling by the
      receivers and 3) Certificate Transparency for Verified Mark
      Certificates that includes a preview process.  The BIMI profile
      and policy document should be reviewed and published through a
      policy directing body such as the CA/Browser Forum or the
      AuthIndicators Working Group.  The protocol to fetch and handle
      Verified Mark Certificate by the receivers document should be
      reviewed and published by the IETF.  Lastly the concept of CT
      logging with preview needs detailed review by the community and
      may be submitted at an academic conference/workshop.  Assuming a
      satisfactory outcome, the final form of the preview work too
      should be published through the IETF.
    </t>
</section>


<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
this document are to be interpreted as described in
<xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>




</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?> <!-- Keywords -->
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2397"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3709"?> <!-- Logotype x-->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?> <!-- X.509 Certificates x-->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6170"?> <!-- Logotype (2) x -->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6376"?> <!-- DKIM X-->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6962"?> <!-- CT -->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7208"?> <!-- SPF X-->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7489"?> <!-- DMRARC X -->
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.blank-ietf-bimi.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.brotman-ietf-bimi-guidance.xml"?>
</references>
</back>
</rfc>
